this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software are you looking for a better
way to track your engineering backlog do
you want a project management tool
that's both powerful and a joy to use
give clubhouse a try designed for
software teams clubhouse is a fast
modern alternative to conventional
project management tools that are either
too complex are too simple start your
free trial and get two extra free months
at clubhouse io / se radio hello this is
Adam Gordon bell for software
engineering radio today I'm speaking
with Heidi Howard a research fellow in
computer science at the University of
Cambridge how do you welcome to software
engineering radio thank you so much for
having me so today we're gonna talk
about distributed consensus algorithms
and I thought a good place to start is
is with the basics so so what is a
distributed system a distributed system
is basically a concurrent system but
even worse it's a system where multiple
things are happening at the same time
but you can also have failures and a
synchrony so the nodes in the system can
fail and they may or may not come back
up and we also have a synchrony so when
we send messages we don't know exactly
how long they're going to take to get to
their destination or even if they will
get to their destination so it's sort of
like like multiple instances of the same
program running and communicating over a
network is that yeah absolutely
absolutely in the context of a
distributed system
what does consensus mean so can
consensus means making a decision in a
distributed system so that could be
deciding a value in a register or
deciding an ordering of operations to be
applied to a database
and what makes distributed consensus
difficult is the same thing that makes
distributed systems difficult that is
the the asynchrony and the partial
failures if we had a purely reliable
system that was super synchronous then
consensus would be really easy to solve
but unfortunately computers don't work
like that in reality so what does it
mean to have consensus is just agreement
so consensus has three components so the
first one is that the value you agree is
the value that somebody proposed it
should be so that's kind of the
non-trivial T component there is a
safety component so when you decide a
value that's final everyone finds out
the same value and thirdly there is a
progress component so that means that if
everything's working okay in the system
the system will reach a decision so the
system can't get itself stuck
indefinitely in a deadlock so when do we
need consensus in a distributed system
do we always need it is there specific
use cases that we don't always need it
because it could be quite expensive in
practice in terms of the number of
messages and and stuff that's needed you
need consensus when you have to have
strong consistency guarantees so for
example if you have a key value store
and you need to have linearize ability
you can't just have like cause or
consistency or something like that you
absolutely have to have linearize
ability so it could be holding some
really critical data in your system it
could be data that's for like
configuration or orchestration we're
sacrificing consistency is just not okay
and you need consensus if you can't rely
on synchrony of clocks so for example
Google doesn't always need consensus
they use a system called spanner this
uses clocks basically because Google
controls the data center so they've put
atomic clocks and GPS receivers into
their data centers instead of relying on
normal time protocols and that means
they don't need consensus either is that
because if they all agree on the exact
time stamps they can put things in order
even though they take place in different
places yeah absolutely
like they
they don't rely on it being perfect but
it's very very close to perfect so as
long as the timestamps are consistent to
within a very small margin then that's
absolutely fine in the system will run
and that allows the system to be much
more efficient a much more lightweight
than a proper distributed consensus
system one thing that I find confusing
maybe is just consensus and consistency
they both start with C's and are they
the same thing or I'm familiar with the
cap theorem which I believe has to do
with consistency out of consensus and
consistency relate consensus is the
method of achieving very strong
consistency and how does the cap theorem
in terms of the cap theorem when we're
looking at consensus we're getting
strong consistency so we're not
compromising consistency we are however
compromising availability so typical
consensus systems use majorities which
means that if say three participants in
a system of five participants go down
the system is unable to be available and
so you've sacrificed availability in
that case so it's more of a is a CP
system in that kind of set of
terminology so in a in a distributed
consensus system there's an it's not
possible to be highly available is that
right your ma I think the comparison
usually because you're getting the
strong consistency guaranteed a
comparison is usually between having one
server or having three servers or five
servers and using consensus so you have
better availability than you would have
had with just one server so it's it's
improved availability compared to one
server whether whether it's improved
enough to be considered high
availability I think depends on the
situation
if those servers are in different
availability zones for example and you
can tolerate failure of one that seems
pretty pretty highly available to me so
it because you just need the majority up
so if you scale up to more nodes then it
can still be sort of highly available am
I getting this right right so if you
have three notes you can tolerate one
failure if you scale up to five nodes
you could
tolerate two failures and up to seven
you could tolerate three and people
don't tend to scale further than that
really
why not because whenever you're doing
something you need to use the mature
that majority of participants you need
to get the majority of participants to
basically agree back you with what
you're doing so as you scale the system
the size of the majority goes up and up
and therefore the latency and the amount
of messages that you need to exchange to
get anything done gets higher and higher
well that's interesting so the
throughput like of Rights for instance
decreases the more nodes you have
because you jority absolutely it's it's
the opposite of a scalable system for
the best performance you would have one
node that is interesting so at my work I
sometimes work on this distributed
system and it has this like it's a Java
program it has this like leadership
annotation so like I can say like I need
to do something I only need to do I need
to make sure it happens on startup but
like only once and so there's this I
just have to say I think it's the code
like leader only I can kind of annotate
that and that's where I kind of do
things like if I need to do some data
migration that's kind of shared data I
will do that there what happens in sort
of a process like that like what does
that mean to say the leader only does
this what is leadership election okay so
leadership election is basically
deciding who's gonna be the person to
make decisions in a distributed sense so
it is there are some political analogies
that are of true you know I've probably
turned out to draw on too much but
basically the participants in the system
design decide between themselves who is
able to act on their behalf if they
decided this every time anything needed
to be done it would take a long time to
get anything done so before the system
needs to do things it decides who's
gonna be in charge who's going to be
responsible for making those decisions
that is the leader of the system and
typically in consensus systems where
we're using majorities the leader backs
up all their decisions to a majority of
the other participants
and then if the leader fails there's a
backup on at least the majority of the
participants so is it in fact like a
voting process
it's called leadership election is the
nodes voting where they absolutely are
voting they we use some mechanisms to
basically allow participants to vote
multiple times if they need to and these
things like views ballots or term
numbers depending on what academic paper
you're you're looking at so that they
can still make progress so we don't ever
end up in a deadlock situation where
half the participants are voted for one
leader and the other half voted for a
different leader so I think that kind of
gives me an understanding of what
distributed consensus is so I thought it
might be fun to take like a historical
perspective on this in part because I
saw taki gave that kind of had that that
feel to it so what was the what was the
first solution you're aware of to
distributed consensus that's that's
quite an interesting and contentious
question actually because there was
quite a few different people who
proposed consensus at a similar ash time
so we're talking late 80s and a lot of
the consensus algorithms were kind of
buried in other academic papers papers
about things like transactions and they
weren't necessarily noticed the paper
that is kind of iconic for pioneering
distributed consensus is a paper called
the part-time Parliament by cheering
Award winner Lesley Lamport yeah he was
he was a guest on se radio episode 2:03
so listeners concerned they check that
out
so what is the the Paxos algorithm so
the packs without groom is kind of this
algorithm that we've been describing so
far it's an algorithm that has two
phases in the first phase the majority
of people get together and just elect
one of the participants to be the leader
to be the person who's going to choose
values in the future and in the second
phase the leader chooses a value and
they back that value up to the majority
of participants this means that if that
leader fails they can communicate with
the participants the participants
communicate between themselves sorry
and
a new leader and as long as a majority
are involved in choosing a new leader we
can be sure that at least one of those
people who votes for a loot new leader
will know about what the last leader did
you mentioned earlier banner what what
systems use Paxos like practical
distributed systems soap access is very
widely used it's used in chubbie which
is used it's just a Google system it's
used in Cassandra it's what can talk
about Paxos versus roughed in a bit but
it's it's the same or very similar to
the raft algorithm which is used in EDD
which is used in kubernetes it's very
similar to the SAP algorithm which is in
zookeeper it's very very widely used
typically just for coordination and
orchestration so if I am using a paxos
system and like let's say it has three
nodes like your previous example and I
go I'm a client and I try to write a
value like what happens there do I have
to go to the leader yeah so you send
your write request to the leader the
leader will then place it in a kind of
sequence of write requests that it's
received and it will then send a message
to the other participant saying that
they should insert that write in those
given position in kind of the history of
what's happened in the system into their
logs the other participants will do that
right and then once majority have got
back the leader will commit that right
so if it's got like say a state machine
there like a replica or if a key value
store it will apply the request and it
will return to you an acknowledgement
that it's been successful and if I try
to read that value back is how does it
work where if I only have to write it to
the majority of nodes isn't there a
chance if I tried to read I could access
the value that's not part of that
majority so it depends how you implement
the reads the proper theoretically the
proper way to implement reads is to
achieve consensus over the reads as well
so they also get a position inside the
log the leader will basically check that
they still are a leader they're still up
to date they still know everything
about what's happened in the system and
then they will apply the read and that
guarantees you linearizable reads as
well as writes typically in practice
though because systems have generally
read heavy we implement route we're a
bit more relaxed in the way we implement
reads so for example you would send the
read just to the master and the master
will give send you back a response and
as long as that master is still the
master in the system that will be a
consistent response and what if I have
like two clients and they each try to
write the same value in some time span
that's very close I guess yeah so from a
consensus perspective those both of
those rights will be successful and they
will happen in a order it doesn't limit
what order will be it will happen in but
it will definitely appear as if one
happened then they ever happened or vice
versa so there won't be you won't end up
with an inconsistent state in the system
it's definitely the case that all the
replicas in the system will see those
rights in the same order but linearise
ability doesn't guarantee a particular
ordering over concurrent rights only
over rights that happen at different
times are there cases where a right
could fail so we can fail if the system
is unavailable so if there are two out
of three participants served down
perhaps you contact the leader but the
other two nodes are down the leader
isn't able to commit that right that
would be a failed right but as long as
the systems up the reads will get placed
in some sort of order so you mentioned
chubbie which i think is a google paper
or system it's a it's a google it's a
Google paper about a Google system yep
so what innovation did Google bring to
the world of distributed consensus if
any Google was probably the first
company that publicly came out and said
like we are implementing pacts offs and
we are deploying it at scale here is the
story of how we did it his the
engineering solutions we came up with to
some of the problems to do with
implementing
Paxos in practice and what were some of
those challenges and problems I
so some of the problems would be things
like we're reaching agreement about a
sequence of operations so that sequence
of operations just keeps growing and
growing indefinitely and at some point
you need to kind of compact that
sequence or you need to snap shot it so
that you don't end up just using an
infinite amount of memory I heard this
term before Multi Paxos what does that
mean so multi packs this is actually
what we've been describing so far so
people tend to use the term as packs or
some multi packs or synonymously so
that's the idea that you establish
leader in the system and that system
will go that leader sorry will go on to
make many decisions in the system single
degree Paxos or like the vanilla pack
source or classic pack sauce is where
you have the leader just make one
decision and then next time you elect
someone new and you have them make one
decision so it's basically you run a
kind of distinct instance of Paxos every
time you need to make a decision each of
those instances it's is basically
disconnected and was this multi paxos
like was this Google's innovation or was
this in the original paper multi it was
in the original paper it was a little
bit it was a little bit hidden in the
original paper just like back so
supposed to be honest but Lumpur lays it
out quite clearly in the in his pencils
made simple which is his paper to kind
of try to explain the part-time
parliment paper a bit more a bit bit
more clearly and earlier you mentioned
zookeeper and I think some consistency
algorithm that it used I thought it used
Paxos is that incorrect it's four it
depends who you talk to
basically so zookeeper uses an algorithm
called Zapp which stands for zookeeper
atomic broadcast that algorithm solves
atomic broadcast which has been shown to
be equivalent to multivariate consensus
sab is very very similar to the multi
Paxos algorithm that we've been
discussing so far there's a few kind of
design decisions they're a little bit
different but the general idea of
electing a leader using majorities and
that leader than taking decisions on
behalf of the system is the same what is
atomic broadcast atomic broadcast
is the idea that if you send messages
within a system everybody will see the
messages in the same order regardless of
the asynchrony in the system ah so the
reason it's the same as kind of it's
what you were saying the leader kind of
orders them and then distributes them
out to the nodes yeah absolutely
if you had an OS and network that gave
you atomic broadcast you could implement
consensus really drivel II by just
allowing anyone to send their operation
as a message and then everyone would see
exactly the same set of operations in
the same order interesting you mentioned
at CD and raft so is is raft a variation
on Paxos or something completely
different again depends who you ask my
perspective is very much that raft is a
really good well articulated description
and simplified version of Paxos
specifically designed for using with
state machine replication which is by
far the most common application of Paxos
in practice I know some people talk
about raft and paxos as if they're
completely separate and completely
different algorithms that's not that's
definitely not view that I would agree
with but raft is definitely very nice
very nice paper it's very nice algorithm
and it was in fact my introduction to
the field of distributed consensus so
how can it be a different algorithm and
be the same the devil is in the detail
the basic basic kind of core idea is the
same and because part time Parliament
was such a we're so under specified you
can basically make the case that it's
the same as most anything that you you
come up with because it was quite quite
vague in what it said the good thing
about raft is that it's quite specific
unlike a lot of the theoretical computer
science work so raft is about
replicating state machines and agreeing
an order of operations to pass into
those state machines and it uses lots of
examples of key value stores and I think
that yeah that made it that's made it
the famous paper that it now is
so is it a good starting place if
somebody wanted to understand these
algorithms it sounds like it's just
better specified I think yeah I do think
it's a really good starting point for
for understanding the kind of basics of
paxos I think that people do struggle
after reading raft as to where to go
next and if I needed a recommendation
for for that I would say there's a good
paper called paxos made moderately
complex which describes paxos and some
of the big famous variants to the paxos
algorithm it's kind of a survey or
overview of what's out there and from
then you could then bootstrap into
consensus out different types different
families of consensus algorithms
depending on on your needs I still find
this terminology confusing because like
so sed says it uses the raft protocol
and then like I think like Cassandra
says it uses Paxos but you're saying
these are the same really it's it's more
of an implementation perspective or yeah
yeah yeah so are there any variations on
these algorithms that should be
preferred in certain situations versus
others yeah definitely so there's a
different different kind of family of
algorithms the main algorithm in that
family is called fast pack sauce and
this group of algorithms basically uses
bigger chorim's so instead of using
majorities it might use say two-thirds
of participants but it removes the
leader from the system so it goes from a
centralized approach to a decentralized
approach and that family has other
algorithms in it like generalized
consensus or a gala terian Paxos and
those are good algorithms if latency is
really important to use if you were
implementing consensus across data
centers
there's definitely something I would
recommend so if we were implementing it
across data centers would we still want
to keep a low number of nodes I think
before you said never more than five or
something like that yeah yeah so I think
if you're using majority quorums it's
the system's running it was the bigger
you make it so I would say I would say
five is a good number
some people do three
some people do seven I don't really see
people using nine and above if you did
want to span more nodes then some of the
work that I've did a couple of years ago
it's known as flexible paxos and this is
about allowing some flexibility in Paxos
algorithms as it says on the tin by
allowing you to use different quorum so
instead of using majorities you can use
different group sizes and that allows
you to then scale up consensus more than
if you were using majorities so this is
your contribution to the field like how
is it different
what is the advantage of being able to
choose a different majority so Paxos
gives you one option in terms of trading
the performance of the system against
fault tolerance you use majorities you
can tolerate minority failures but if
you had say seven a system of seven
nodes what you could do instead of using
a quorum of four which is the majority
you could use a quorum of three it's a
smaller quorum which means there's less
messages and it could be more performant
in some cases it may tolerate one less
failure so it would only tolerate two
failures instead of three but depending
on the system you can get some really
interesting performance gains from that
so what flex will paxos does is
basically open up packs offs and say you
can choose that trade-off that you want
to make versus Paxos says this is the
one trade-off that you have and this
will fit all systems so is this
algorithm in usage yeah yeah absolutely
so I've seen various kind of discussions
of it people have implemented it so
there was a master student that
implemented it into zookeeper and there
yeah if you google it online for us
other people have implemented it there's
a team that are using it to do geo
replicated consensus their algorithm is
called W Paxos yeah so lots of I
implemented it myself as well I built it
on top of implementation called limp
axles although that's predominantly for
kind of benchmarking and testing
we've been talking about these consensus
algorithms I guess with the assumption
that they work like how is that
demonstrated that's a really good
question so it's quite hard to reason
about what's going on with these
algorithms because they really are quite
quite subtle the tool that I use the
same tool that all people in the field
use is known as TLA plus it was also
vented by Leslie Lamport so shocking
means it's good for expressing consensus
algorithms and what it does is it allows
you to write the algorithm and then it
allows you to model check that
specification of the algorithm so you
can come up with a property say at most
one value is decided in any slot in a
sequence and then you can check for a
kind of small configuration that that's
true regardless of what happens in the
system that's quite a nice way of
getting you to think carefully about the
algorithm and reasoning about edge cases
but it is limited in the sense that you
model check for a specific number of
nodes so you check for five nodes or for
seven nodes if you want to check more
comprehensively you can move on to using
a theorem prover so there's T laps which
is their improver over T la Plus
otherwise this theorem provers the one
developed by Cambridge University School
Isabel and there's another one this
written a no camel which is called cog
and they allow you to prove properties
of consensus algorithms this again is
very nice it allows you to reason about
edge cases but you then still have to
hand over the algorithm to two engineers
to implement and then you know who knows
that's implemented correctly and so I'm
a huge fan of the work of Calkins buri
which is probably further so if your
listeners who are interested in
databases mm-hmm and his Jessop system
where he tests various databases and key
value stores and he tests them for
linear writes ability and I doesn't
really good really good work in terms of
checking whether these algorithms
actually do what they say in the to say
on the tin and he's tested
and at CG I believe yeah I think that he
was a guest I don't have the number but
all I'll find it so what he does is
actually real-world testing is T la Plus
like a simulation is that how you would
describe it or is it a proof it's I
guess it's kind of like a simulation so
you write the algorithm in there
especially in the special ta+ language
and then you basically you model check
which is simulation but it's just
exhaustive simulation so you check all
possible scenarios is quite
computationally instead so as you can
imagine Oh an interesting thing I was
noticing I was looking at some
benchmarks online of zookeeper versus
@cd versus a couple other systems and
then looking at them versus like a more
traditional like key value store and
they seem to be not there they're
obviously slower because consensus has
to be reached but not too bad but what I
noticed is there's big spikes in like
latency like occasionally a write takes
a long time I wondered if there was
something to do with reaching consensus
that can cause like unpredictable times
for updates yes so there's definitely
stuff that that can that can go wrong in
practice that could leave to a high
latency so probably the most common
would be a failure of the leader or just
a suspected failure of the leader so if
there was say a bit of congestion in the
network and the other participants
accidentally believed that the leader
had failed and they go on to try and
elect a new leader that can take quite
really quite a long time and it's quite
funny because you know no no failures of
actual of actual participants in your
system need to occur for your system to
actually believe that there's a failure
and then suffer the high latency as a
result yeah earlier you mentioned like
multi data center consistency it seems
like that would be a challenge with with
the latency and possibly like losing
contact is this being done in practice
like consistency across data centers
yeah it is it is so Google mega store
and is paxos influence Paxos across data
centers it's it is hard it is tricky I
think what usually happens is that
because we don't want to accidentally
believe a leader has failed we set
timers for how often we heart be the
leader and how long we're willing to
wait before we start reporting this
leader as having failed we have in a Geo
replicated setting we have to set those
timers quite high to stop those false
failure detection detection the downside
of this of course is that when a failure
does happen and the leader does go down
the system will wait a long time
unnecessarily just to be a hundred
percent sure that that leader has gone
down well 99% sure you can never be a
hundred percent sure of anything in
distributed systems
so you mentioned time outs in a
distributed system I think I I saw in a
talk of yours something called the FLP
result which I believe showed that
reaching consensus could be impossible
is that right yes that's right so quite
entertainingly the FLP result was
basically the paper that founded the
field of distributed consensus so paper
that said this thing is impossible led
to decades of researchers trying to
prove the authors wrong and what that
paper says is that it's impossible to
guarantee consensus in a system where
even one participant might fail which is
interesting because it doesn't even say
one participant fails if there's just
the possibility that a participant might
fail you can't guarantee consensus so
that means you can't be sure that
consensus will happen within a bounded
time period so I don't get then if it's
impossible how is this resolved or was
it we don't get guaranteed consensus in
practice in practice we do things like
we have we use timers and we set them
quite high and we all when we send a
message instead of we use things like
TCP and we say we just assume the
message will get there within a year and
that allows us to
circumvent the FOP result in practice
and why why does the FLP result results
suggest that it's impossible it's
impossible because we can't guarantee
within like a fixed time period that we
will be able to get consensus so we
can't definitely say like it is gonna
happen in this amount of time which
makes sense when we can't even guarantee
that a message will get to somewhere
within a fixed amount of time so we
definitely can't guarantee that many
messages will have got too many
different places within a fixed amount
of time so is it related to this idea
like I can't tell if you're still there
because you might be there but just not
getting my my requests yeah yep um so
how did you get interested in this field
so I came across the rough paper whilst
I was doing my undergraduate and I read
the paper and I thought it was really
interesting and I was really excited by
the idea of consensus and at this point
the paper was just a draft online it
hadn't been published or anything like
that and I like many people wanted to go
away and implement it so I did I
implemented it in my favorite language
at the time which is okay was work was
is Oh camel and in that implementation I
came up with like what I thought was
some cool novel optimizations to the
algorithm to make the performance better
so I implemented those and I started
telling people about them very very
excited I was and then people were like
this is all known stuff this is like
what people use with Paxos all the time
and you need to go away and do a lot of
reading about Paxos and consensus before
you can start optimizing consensus
algorithms so I went away and I read
various algorithms on consensus I also
started giving some talks about those
papers that I'd read because I don't
think you really I think you really know
something until you try to teach it to
somebody else and from there I got more
and more interested in consensus
algorithms and how we could optimize
their performance in practice is the
danger with your early optimizations
just that they would make it you know
not always consistent in some way that
you didn't perceive not normally
mostly they're just complicated and they
take away from the point of raft the
whole point of raft is that it it puts
simplicity first and they say upfront in
the paper they say you know well we had
a choice between performance and
understandability we chose
understandability so I was basically
just putting back in all of the stuff
that they had taken out from paxos and I
was putting it back in to try to make it
more efficient there is definitely a
definitely a challenge with ensuring the
safety of optimizations particularly
when people start to use clocks and rely
on clocks so things like master leases
as a software engineer chances are
you've crossed paths with MongoDB at
some point whether you're building an
app for millions of users are just
figuring out a side hustle as the most
popular non relational database MongoDB
is intuitive and incredibly easy for
development teams to use now with
MongoDB Atlas you can take advantage of
MongoDB flexible document data model as
a fully automated cloud service MongoDB
Atlas handles all the costly database
operations and admin tasks you'd rather
not spend time on like security high
availability data recovery monitoring
and elastic scaling try MongoDB Atlas
for free today
visit MongoDB comm slash cloud to learn
more when when we talk about an
innovation like you're flexible paxos
like what is coming up with that involve
are you using the TI plus that you
discussed sir you just have an idea or
what is your steps so the story of a
flexible practice is quite a funny one
so I was in it was three summers ago I
went to vmware research in in palo alto
california to work with dolly and monkey
who's a very famous computer scientists
in the field of distributed consensus
and she wanted me to work on an area
known as Byzantine fault tolerance so
that is the type of consensus that fuels
to blockchain and whilst I was kind of
trying to get my head together with
Byzantine fault tolerance I was also
trying to put together a talk to kind of
introduce myself to the team about
and how it works and how do we teach
Paxos from real like first principles
Lamport has this famous quote where he
says that
paxos is practice is inevitable you know
if you just think about consensus you
would derive Paxos and so I was trying
to kind of put that to the test and
whilst I was doing it and I'm also
trying to prove it
using kind of pen and paper proof I
couldn't see why we needed to use
majorities for consensus and I went
through a good few weeks of just
thinking oh my gosh I don't understand
paxos this is a thing I think going
around and talking to people about and
like I've been telling people about
consensus and people assume that I know
but I just I can't understand why we
need majorities so I definitely spent
quite a while scratching my head
assuming I was just missing something
and eventually I got the bravery
together to go to my colleague Dahlia
monkey and say like why whose pixels
need to use majority quorums and
initially she was like well you know for
safety's it's obvious and then I was
like but why for safety and she thought
about it and she was like you you don't
need them you don't need them the court
the requirement about quorums is weaker
than them what paxos uses and so then we
expressed it in TLA plus i was it was
pretty easy to express because Lamport
actually written a Paxos implementation
into la plus so varying that for
flexible Paxos was quite straightforward
and then we wrote up a paper and sent it
around and it was very helpful to have
done the tli plus stuff and to have a
famous computer scientist like Dahlia
kind of backing that works try and
convince other people that it was true
because I think for a lot of people's
initial reaction was like what is this
what are you talking about everyone
knows packed cells needs to use
majorities for safety wow it sounds like
quite an exciting time I think isn't it
true that the original like Paxos paper
took a long time to gain acceptance yes
yes it is so I think it was seven years
remembering correctly that the paper I
think some versions of it had like been
distributed to some people but it wasn't
formally published for
for a long long time it's still I think
once it was published Butler Lampson I
believe wrote a paper about
lamport's paxos paper and really kind of
and mumble had already got a good
reputation for his work in distributed
systems that it really like as soon as
it was available I really took off very
quickly if you're using this TL A+ to
show something like that the majority is
not needed like why is is getting
accepted tired like isn't that a
demonstration because it's very hard to
convince people that stuff they've
believed to be true for a long time
isn't true and a lot of the descriptions
of paxos bake the idea of majorities
right into the very definition of what
it means to reach consensus and
therefore the idea of not having them is
is crazy and with TL a-plus like it does
have its limitations so like I said when
you check a model you specify a number
of notes so you can't show for all
possible and where n is the number of
notes you can say I've checked for three
and five and seven but I can't say that
it's true in a general case did you end
up showing it's true in a general case
using another tool at another time
so I've done a pen and paper kind of
paper boof where you kind of break it
down and and I've washed out over a few
pages and that's something people have
been very been happy enough with once
you once you once you find the right way
of explaining it you can easily make
quite a convincing case for flexible
paxos what I'm actually one of the
things I'm working on at the moment is
learning to use
Isabeau which is a their improver so
that I can prove these things in the
general case it's one of those things or
it takes a long time to learn and it's
quite a difficult tool but hopefully
once I've once I've got it
I'll be able to use a again and again to
show consider correctness or the in
correctness of consensus algorithms and
are there future innovations and
consensus algorithms expected in the
paper recently which is called the
generalized solution to distributed
consensus and what it does is it breaks
Consensus such that it only uses
immutable registers the good thing about
only using immutable registers is that
when you have immutability it's a lot
easier to see what's going on and if you
read a register you know that that value
will always be the same by switching to
that representation of using immutable
registers it's become apparent that
there are even more consensus algorithms
that are correct than I originally
thought and so at the moment it's just a
case of exploring specific points in
that space so the area is not like
totally explored no no definitely not
and beyond kind of the consensus I
currently work on which is non Byzantine
consensus there is Byzantine consensus
so this is where participants can act
maliciously or just arbitrarily
Byzantine consensus has been around for
a very long time but is now getting a
lot of interest because of blockchain
and cryptocurrencies
how does blockchain and consensus really
I'm not clear on that so in the
blockchain generally what happens is you
use some process like proof of work to
elect a committee and that committee
makes decisions using Byzantine fault
tolerant consensus algorithm such as
pbft practical Byzantine fault tolerance
and in that algorithm it basically uses
extra round trips and the signing of
messages to keep a record each
participant basin keeps a record of what
all the other participants in the system
are doing so that when you reach
consensus so you can reach consensus
whilst tolerating the fact that some of
those participants might have lied to
you it is more even more heavyweight
than normal consensus why would you be
concerned that nodes my lie to you
because you don't know who's who's
operating who's operating that node so
with the kind of consensus I usually
work on you control all the nodes and
they're in your datacenter and everybody
is able to trust everyone else but out
in the real world you know different
people are operating different machines
also you know programs contain books
and if you're using Byzantine fault
tolerance to build say a cryptocurrency
what you've got is some really motivated
attackers who would be willing to put a
lot of resources in to try to compromise
some of those hosts and take over the
distributed consensus component yeah so
in a like in a zookeeper system like I
control all the nodes and I don't have
to worry about them misbehaving is there
value for kind of the zookeeper scenario
some of the breakthroughs in the
blockchain area like what it never makes
sense to have zookeeper be able to
handle adversarial nodes or something so
people are working on this there is
Byzantine fault tolerant versions of
raft it's an it's not my speciality my
PhD was entirely in the non Byzantine
space I personally think that the best
Byzantine consensus algorithms are
leaderless though decentralized because
if you have a leader it just makes a lot
harder to construct a Byzantine
consensus algorithm because you have to
deal with the fact that that leader that
pointer centralization in your system
might lie whereas if you have a
decentralized system I think it's much
easier to tolerate lies and a malicious
participants is their performance
ramifications if you don't have a leader
as is it more complicated or or slower
it is generally a little bit slower like
if you take something like fast pack
sauce which is a fast packs also slower
fast facts versus larger quorum so it
might say two-thirds of participants
have to agree something before it can
happen instead of saying just over half
of the participants have to have to
agree performance can perform install so
be less reliable so in an algorithm like
fast pack sauce you can end up with
situations where because you don't have
a leader you have two people trying to
do to do something at the same time and
they conflict and one of them has to
back off and try again so we've heard
about variations on on distributed
consensus like what does the future hold
like I'm a software developer the
listeners are as well can we expect what
a faster zookeeper some new breakthrough
I've never heard of everything rights to
the blockchain
where do you think things are heading I
think we're heading towards a world
where we have more options in terms of
distributed consensus that are
specialized to different scenarios so at
the moment we really in practice we
mostly have paxos and its variants and
they're all use majorities and they're
all leader based and I think we're gonna
see more and more different options that
come available so with fast paxos for
example you can use different types of
quorums across where you've got multiple
nodes across different data centers and
within data centers so that you could
tolerate a data center failure for
example and so I think we're gonna see a
lot more variation as people come to
understand consensus algorithms more and
more and also you know if depending on
whether you want to have a right TV
workload versus whether you have a read
heavy workload you might want to use
different consensus algorithm whether if
you've got a key value store and there's
a lot of locality and accesses you may
want to use a different kind of
consensus algorithm too if there wasn't
so it really depends on on the
application and the trade-offs you're
willing to make so my big hope for the
future is that that you know you have to
make compromises in distributed systems
but you should at least get to choose
which compromises you make instead of
having to take Paxos as it is and I'm
right at the beginning you mentioned
Google spanner and how does their
approach from this differ they're kind
of rethinking some of the assumptions
about networks or time yeah so in Google
spanner the protocol actually makes use
of clocks and relies on clock synchrony
to some extent for safety which is very
different from consensus Google are able
to do this because they put atomic
clocks and all their data centers and so
it's a reasonable assumption to assume
that those clocks are pretty close to
synchronized but that's not an
assumption that everybody can make with
their normal machines that are using ntp
say just first for time synchronization
and what about if if networks become
more reliable with that influence these
algorithms yeah I mean if if we could
get a lot stronger
guarantees about the synchrony and
network so if we could say with a very
very high degree of certainty that a
message will be delivered within a
fairly small time bound we would be able
to develop much better systems I think
so for example we could detect failures
of participants a lot more quickly if we
didn't have such variation in network
latency because we'd have a tighter
timeout yeah absolutely and what's your
future work what are you working on so
as I said before I'm working a bit on
Isabelle and learning about using
theorem provers I'm also looking to
learn more about Byzantine fault
tolerance and if we can apply flexible
Paxos and generalize consensus and some
of the ideas from non Byzantine
consensus to Byzantine consensus so you
you started with reading this RAF paper
has an undergraduate what what did you
think it would be like then getting into
this field and and how is it actually
played out I never really had a plan I
did not plan to to go into this field I
just read the RAF paper because I was
interested and then I was was really
interested so I implemented it and then
I thought about it a lot it wasn't it
wasn't my plan to do a PhD on dish B
consensus it was my plan to do a PhD on
kind of peer to peer edge of cloud
computing at the edge and to build these
massive systems and solving consensus
was a tiny tiny tiny component of that I
guess I expected in my head that that
consensus would be a couple of pages of
my PhD thesis instead of 150 pages so I
do thank you for coming on the show
where where can listeners find you
online if they want to reach out to you
so mostly I'm on twitter my handle is
heidi and 360 and will include that in
the show notes along with some of these
links this is adam gordon bell for
software engineering radio thank you for
listening
thanks for listening to se radio an
educational program brought to you by
out your police software magazine for
more about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website @ SC - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of SU radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening